<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godlye medytacyon composed by the faithfull ... I.B. latlye burnte in Smytfelde  ...</title>
            <author>Bradford, John, 1510?-1555.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1559</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16579</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3483</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109638</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845285</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845285</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10176</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16579)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10176)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 178:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godlye medytacyon composed by the faithfull ... I.B. latlye burnte in Smytfelde  ...</title>
                  <author>Bradford, John, 1510?-1555.</author>
                  <author>Vives, Juan Luis, 1492-1540. Excitationes in animi Deum. aut</author>
                  <author>Pownall, Robert, 1520-1571. Most fruitful prayer for the dispersed church of Christ. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[84] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Saint Martins parishe in the vinetre, vpon the three Crane warfe, by wyllyam Coplande,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. Do. M.D.LIX. The vx. daye of Marche. [1559]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.B. = Iohn Bradford.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Largely translated from: Vives, Juan Luis. Excitationes animi in Deum.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: of Iohn Bradforth. A godly meditacion.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F² .</note>
                  <note>Title page mutilated with partial loss of print; considerable print show-through; leaves marked and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10176:1"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Godlye <hi>Medytacyon compoſed by the</hi> faithfull and conſtant ſeruant of God I. B. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> laſtlye was burnte in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for the teſtimonie of Ieſus Chriſte, by the tyrannye of Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte in his fyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>¶ Pſalme lxxix.</bibl>
O Lorde let the vengeaunce of thy ſeruauntes bloude that is ſhedde be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penlye ſhowed vpon the vngodlye in oure ſight. O let the ſorowful, ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the priſoners come before thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and accordinge to the greatnes of thy power preſerue thou thoſe that are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to dye.</q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10176:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10176:2"/>
            <p>O Almightye and euerlaſting Lord god the deer father of our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, which haſte made heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; earth, the ſea and al that therin is, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che art the onely ruler, gouernor, conſeruor, &amp; keper of all thinges, together with thy deerly beloued ſonne Chriſt Ieſus our lord, and with thy holy ghoſte the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forter. O holy, Righteous and wyſe. O ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, terrible, mighty and ferfull Lorde god, iudge of all men, and gouernour of al the whole world O exorable, pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious father, whoſe eyes ar vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wayes of all men, and are ſo cleane, they cannot a byede impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, thou ſearcheſt the hartes and tryeſt the verye thaughtes, and raynes of all men, thou hateſt ſin and abhorreſt iniquitie: for ſyns ſake thou haſte greuouſly puniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb facs="tcp:10176:3"/>
mankind thy moſt dere crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture as thou haſte declared by the penalty of death layed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the children of Adam, by the caſtyng out of Adam &amp; his of ſpring forth of Paradice, by the curſing of the earthe, by the drowninge of the world, by the burning vp of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and gomor, by the hardning the harte of Pharao, ſo that no miracle could co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert him, by the drowning of hym, and his people w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him in the red ſea, by the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing of the Iſrahelytes in the wildernes, ſo that of ſyx hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth thouſand, all onely but two did enter into the land of promis, by reiecting kinge Saule, by the greate poniſhmentes vppon thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t dauid, not withſtanding his harty repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance by greuouſly aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cting Salamon in him ſelfe, and in his poſteritie: by the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie
<pb facs="tcp:10176:3"/>
of the ten tribes, and by the thraldom of the Iewes, wherein vntill this preſent daye they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue a notable ſpectacle, of they wrath to the worlde agaynſt and for ſinne, but of all ſpectacles of thy angre agaynſt ſin, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt and moſte notable, is the death &amp; bloudy paſſion of thy deerly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſon Iheſus Chriſt. Greate is thine angre agaynſt ſyn when in heauen and earth nothing could befou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d which might appeaſe thy wrath, ſaue the bloudſheading of thyne onely &amp; moſte deerly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſon, in whome was and is al thy delight, great is the ſore of ſin that needed ſuche a ſalue, mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was the mallady, that needed ſuche a medicine. Yf in Chriſte in whome was no ſynne, thy wrath was ſo ferce for our ſinne, that he was conſtreyned to crye my god,
<pb facs="tcp:10176:4"/>
my god why haſte thou forſaken me, howe greate and importable then is thyne angre agaynſte vs whiche are nothinge but ſinfull. They that ar thy childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through the contemplation of thyne angre againſt ſinne, ſet forthe moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently in the death of Chriſt, Do tremble &amp; ar affraide, lamenting them ſelues vppon him (and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely cryeng for mercy) Where as the wicked, ar altogether careles &amp; contemptuous, nothing lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their iniquities or crying to the hartely for mercy and pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, amongſt whome we ar rather to be placed, then amongſt thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, for that we ar ſo ſhameleſſe for our ſyn, and careleſſe for thy wrathe, which we may wel ſay to be moſt greuous againſt vs, and euidently ſet forthe in the taking awaye of our good King and thy
<pb facs="tcp:10176:4"/>
true religion, in thexiel of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, pryſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thy people, myſery of thy children, and death of thy ſainctes. Alſo by the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinge ouer vs in Aucthoritie thy enemies, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſucceſſe thou geueſt them in all they take in hande, by the returninge agayne in to our countrey of Antechriſt the pope. All theſe as they do preache vnto all the worlde (but ſpecially vnto vs) thy greuous wrath, ſo do they ſet before our eyes, our iniquities and ſinnes, which haue deſerued the ſame, for thou arte Iuſte and holy in all thy workes thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes ar righteous altogether, it is we, it is we that haue ſinned, &amp; procured theſe plages we haue ben vnthankfull wretches, and moſte carnall goſſpelers therfore to vs parteyneth ſhame, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge elſe is due but confuſion.
<pb facs="tcp:10176:5"/>
For we haue don very wickedly, we haue heaped ſinne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne, ſo that the meaſure hath ouer flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, and Aſcend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d vp to heauen, and brought theſe plages, which are but earneſt for greater to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, &amp; yet alas we are altogether caerleſſe, in maner, what ſhall we doe? What ſhall we ſay? Who can geue vs pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hartes? Who can open our lips, that our mouthes might make acceptable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion vnto thee. Alas of our ſelues we cannot thinke any good, muche leſſe wiſhe it, and leaſte of all do it, as for Angelles or anye other creatures, they haue nothing, but that which they haue receaued, &amp; they ar made to miniſter vnto vs ſo that where it paſſeth the powre of the maſter, ſhe miniſter muſte nedes want, Alas then what ſhal we doe? Thou arte holy &amp; we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holye,
<pb facs="tcp:10176:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thou arte good, and we no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge but euill, thou arte pure, we all together impure, thou arte light, and we moſte darke darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, how then can ther be any con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueniency or agreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t betwixt vs, O what nowe may we doe? Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre? no, for thou art god, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore good thou art mercyfull, and therfore thou forgeueſt ſinnes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thee is mercye and propiciation, and therefore thou arte worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, when Adam had ſinned thou gaueſt him mercy before he deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it, &amp; wilt thou denye vs mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye whiche nowe deſyer the ſame, Adam excuſed his faulte and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, but we accuſe our ſelues, and excuſe thee, &amp; ſhall we be ſent emptye awaye? Noye founde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor when thy fury a bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyd and ſhal we ſeking grace be fruſtrate? Abraham was pulled oute of
<pb facs="tcp:10176:6"/>
ydolatrye when the worlde was drowned therin, and art thou his god onelye? Iſraell in captiuitie in Egipt was gratiouſlye viſited and deliuered and deer God, the ſame good lord, ſhall we alwaies be forgotten? Howe often in the wildernes diddeſt thou defer, and ſpar thy plages, at the requeſt of Moyſes when the people them ſelues made no petition to thee. And ſeynge we not onelye nowe make our petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnto the throu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghe thy goodneſſe, but alſo haue a mediator for vs now far aboue Moyſes, euen Iheſus Chriſte: ſhould we I ſaye deere lorde, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte aſhamed? So ſoone as Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid ſaid I haue ſinned, thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt forthe wyth anſwer to hym that he ſhould not dye, thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt taken away his ſinnes, And gracious god, euen the ſelfe ſame
<pb facs="tcp:10176:6"/>
god, ſhal not we which now with Dauid gladlye confeſſe that we haue ſinned, ſhall we I ſaye not heare, by thy good ſprite, that our ſynnes be pardoned. O graunte that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Manaſſes we maye finde fauor and mercye remember that thou haſt not ſpared thyne owne onely dereſone Ieſus Chriſt, but geuen hym for vs all to dye, for our ſinnes, to ryſe for our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, to aſſend for our poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taking in heauen, and to appere before thee for vs for euer, a high prieſte after the order of Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadech that throughe hym we might haue fre acceſſe to come to thy throane, now rather of grace then of Iuſtice, Remember that thou by him haſt bidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſke and promiſed that we ſhould receaue, ſaying aſke and ye ſhal haue, ſeke and ye ſhall finde, knocke and it
<pb facs="tcp:10176:7"/>
ſhalbe opened vnto you. O thou Dere god and moſte meke and mercifull father, we hartely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche the to be mercifull vnto vs, for this thy Chriſtis ſake, for his Deathes ſake, for thy promiſſe truethe, and mercyes ſake, haue mercy vpon vs, pardon &amp; forgeue vs al our Sinnes, iniquites, and treſpacis, what ſo euer we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted agaynſt the, in thought word or Dede, euer or at any tyme he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto by any means, Der father haue mercy vpon vs thoughe we be pore, yt our chriſt is Riche, thoughe we be Sinners yet he is righteous, though we be fools, yet is he wiſe, thoughe we be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure yet he is pure, and holye, for his ſake therefore be mercyfull vnto vs, Cal to mynde how thou haſte promiſed that thou wilte powre out of thy cleane waters,
<pb facs="tcp:10176:7"/>
and waſhe vs from our fylth, &amp; clence vs from our euilles, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not that thou haſt promyſed to take from vs our ſtony hartes, &amp; Doeſt promis to geue vs ſauft hartes, newe hartes &amp; to put into the middes of vs right Sprites, Remember thy couenate namely howe thou wilt be our god and we ſhall be thy people, forgette not the partes of it, that is to put owte of thy memory for euer all vnrighteouſnes, and to write in our myndes and hartes thy lawe and teſtymonyes, Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that thou doeſt ſtreightly charg vs to haue none other godes but the, ſaying that thou art the lord our gad. O the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> declare the ſame to vs all, we hartelye nowe beſeche the forgeue vs our ſinnes, forget our iniquitis, clence vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, waſhe vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our wickednes,
<pb facs="tcp:10176:8"/>
powre out thy holy ſprite vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs our harde harts, our ſtony harts, our impenite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t harts, oure diſtruſtinge and doubtfull harts, our carnal our ſecure, our ydle, our beaſtlye hartes, our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, malicious, arrogant, enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, wrathfull, impatient, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, hipocriticall and epicuriall hartes, &amp; in place thereof geue vs newe hartes, ſaft hartes, faithful hartes, mercifull hartes, louing, obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, chaeſt pure, holy, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, trewe ſimple, lowly, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient hartes, to feare thee, to loue thee, truſte in thee for euer, write thy lawe in our hartes, graue it in our mindes, we hertely beſeche the geue vs that ſprite of prayer, make vs diligent &amp; happy in the workes of our vocation, take in to thy cuſtody and gouernaunce for euer, our ſoules and bodyes,
<pb facs="tcp:10176:8"/>
oure lyues, and all that euer we haue, tempt vs neuer further, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou wilt make vs able to beare, &amp; what ſo euer thou knoweſt we haue nede of in ſoul or body, deer god and gracious father, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to geue vs that ſame in thy good tyme and alwayes, as thy children guide vs, ſo that our life maye pleaſe the and our deathes prayſe the through Ieſus Chriſt our lorde, for whoſe ſake we har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely praye the to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges thus aſked, &amp; al other things neceſſary for ſoule and bodye, not only to vs, but to all others alſo, for whome thou woldeſt that we ſhoulde praye, ſpeciallye for they children, that be in thraldom, in exyel, in priſon, miſery, heauines, pouertye, ſycknes. Be mercifull to al the whole realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d graunte vs al trewe repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,
<pb facs="tcp:10176:9"/>
mitigation of our myſerye, and yf it be thy good will, thy holye worde and Religion amongſt vs once agayne, pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our enemies, perſecutors, and ſlaunderers, and yf it be thy pleaſure, turne their hartes, be mercyful vnto our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, Brethern and Siſters, frendes, kinſfolkes and famelis neighbours, and ſuche as by any meanes thou haſte coupled and lincked vs by loue, or otherwyſe, and vnto vs pore ſinners here ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thered together in thy holy name, graunt vs thy bleſſing and holy ſprite to ſanctify vs, and dwel in vs, as thy dere childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to kepe vs, this day and for euer, from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill to thy eternal glory, and our euerlaſting comfort and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet of thy churche, which mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye, maynteyne thereſhe and comforte, ſtrengthning them that
<pb facs="tcp:10176:9"/>
ſtonde, ſo that they neuer fall, lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge vp them that be falne and kepe vs from fallynge, from thy truthe, throughe the merites of thy deerly beloued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our onely ſauiour, which lyueth and Reigneth with the &amp; the holy ghoſt, to whom be all praiſe and honor both nowe and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶When you awake out of your ſlepe pray thus.</head>
               <p>OH moſte dere father of our Sauioure Ieſus Chriſte, whome none doeth know but of thy gift graunt that to the manyfolde greate benefytes of thy goodnes geuen to me, this whiche of all other is moſte, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be added, that like as thou haſte awaked my body from ſlepe, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:10176:10"/>
thou woldeſt throughlye awake yea deliuer mi ſoule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſlepe of ſin and darknes of this world and that whiche now is awaked out of ſlepe, thou wouldeſt, after deathe reſtore to lyfe for that is but ſlepe to the whiche is death to vs, Deere god I moſte harte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly beſeche, and humbly pray thy goodnes, to make my body ſuch a companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or rather a miniſter of godlynes, to my ſoule, in this preſent lyfe, that i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the life to cum it may parte take with the ſame euerlaſtinge happines by Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde. Awake thou that ſleepeſt and ariſe frome the deed, and Chriſt ſhal ſhewe light vnto thee. Epheſians. v.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Occaſions to meditate.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10176:10"/>HEre call to minde the great myrth and bliſſednes, of the euerlaſtynge reſurrection, Alſo remembre to muſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that mooſte cleare lyght and brighte morenynge, and new clearenes of oure bodyes after the longe darkenes it hath ben in, all then ſhalbe full of ioye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> So ſoone as you beholde the daye lyght pray.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lorde thou greateſt and moſte trewe light, whence this lyght of the day and ſunne dothe ſprynge, O lyght whiche doeſt lyghten, euery manne that commeth in to this worlde, Oh lyght whiche knoweſt no nyght nor eueninge, but art alwayes a midday moſt cleere &amp; fayre with out whom al is moſt darke dark<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes bi who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> albe moſt ſple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dent O
<pb facs="tcp:10176:11"/>
thou wiſdome of the eternall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercis, lighten my mind that I maye onely ſe thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that pleaſe the, and maye be blinded to all other thinges.</p>
               <p>Graunte that I maye walke in thy wayes, and that nothing els may be light and pleaſaunt vnto me. Lighten mine eies, Oh lord, that I ſlepe not in deathe, leaſte myne enemies ſaye I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled agaynſt him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Occaſions to meditate.</head>
               <p>MVſe a little how much the light and eye of the minde and ſoule is better then of the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye. Alſo that we care more for the ſoule to ſe well, then for the body. Thinke that beaſtes haue bodely eies and therwith ſe, but men haue eies of the minde and therewith ſhould ſee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10176:11"/>
               <head>¶When you ariſe pray.</head>
               <p>OVre fyrſte father tombled downe him ſelfe, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a moſt excelent high &amp; honorable eſtate into the miex of miſery, and depe ſea of ſhame &amp; miſcheffe, but Oh Chriſt thou putting forthe thine hand dideſt raiſe hym vp, euen ſo we except we be lift vp of the, ſhall lye ſtyll for euer. O good Chriſt our moſt gratious rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as thou doeſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully, reiſe vs now this my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and burden, euen ſoo, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche the raiſe vp my minde and harte to the lighte of the trewe knowledge of the loue of thee, that my conuerſacion may be in heauen wher thou art. Yf thou be riſen, with Chriſte thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe thinges that be aboue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Occaſions to meditate.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10176:12"/>THinke Sum thynge howe fowle and filthye that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams fal was by reaſon of ſynne, and ſo of euerye one of vs from the heigth of goddes grace Againe thinke vpon the greate benefite of Chriſt, by whoſe help wee doe daylye aryſe from our fallynges.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶When you Apparell yourſelfe Praye.</head>
               <p>O Chriſt cloeth me with thin owne ſelfe, that I maye be ſo far from makynge pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion for my fleſhe to fulfyll the luſtes of yt, that I maye cleane put of all my carnal deſiers, and crucefy the kyngdom of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe in me, Be thou vnto me a wede to warme me, from catching the colde of this world, yf thou be a wai fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me (dere lord) al thinges wilbe vnto me forthwith colde,
<pb facs="tcp:10176:12"/>
weake dede. &amp;c. But yf thou be with me al things wilbe warme lyuelye, freſhe. &amp;c. graunt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that as I compas this my body with this cote, ſo thou wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt cloth me wholy (but ſpetial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye my ſoule) wyth thyne owne ſelfe. Put vpon you as the elect of god, bowelles of mercy, meke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, loue, peace. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Occaſions to meditate.</head>
               <p>CAl to mynd a lytle how we are incorperate into chriſt, againe how he doeth cloth vs noriſh vs vnder his wings, p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tettio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, preſerue vs. &amp;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ When you ar made redy, to begyn the day wythall praye.</head>
               <p>O God and mercyful father thou knoweſte and haſte taught vs to knowe ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng, that the weaknes of man is much, and that withoute thy
<pb facs="tcp:10176:13"/>
grace and vertue, he can do nor thinke no good thing, Haue mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy vpon mee, I humbly doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche thee whiche am thy moſte vnworthye, and mooſte weake childe, O be gracious and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der towards me, lighte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me that I maye with pleaſure looke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good thinges onely, exhorte me that I may couet them carefully leade me that I may folow and at the length attaine them, I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſting my ſelfe altogether co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende and offer my ſelfe wholy ſoule, body, life &amp;c. Into thy han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Thy louing ſprite leade me foorth vnto the lande of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Cogitations mete to begyn the daye with.</head>
               <p>THinke firſt that a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of a ſoul and a body, and that the ſoule is from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb facs="tcp:10176:13"/>
heauenly, fyrme and immor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall, but the body is of the earth, earthly, fraile &amp; mortall. Againe thinke that though by reaſon of ſynne wherin you are conceued and borne, the partes of the ſoul that vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth and deſireth be ſo corrupte that without ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall grace to bothe parties, you can neither knowe nor loue any good thinge in gods ſight, much leſſe doe good then, yet this not withſtandinge thinke that you are regenerate by Chriſtes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection (whereof youre bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, requireth fayth and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue both thoſe partes ſum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing reformed bothe to knowe and loue, and therfore to do ſum good in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of God through Chriſt) for whoſe ſake our poore doenges are accepted, for good, the euyl and infirmitie cleauing
<pb facs="tcp:10176:14"/>
therto not beinge imputed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row faith, think y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by faith which is gods ſede (for they which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue are borne of god, and made goddes children) geuen to thoſe that be ordened, to eternall lyfe, thinke (I ſaye) by faith that you receaue more and more, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of ſanctification, throughe the vſe of gods worde and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, and earneſt praier to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumine, and lighten our mindes, vnderſtanding, iudgement and reaſon, &amp; to bowe, forme, frame, and inflame your affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with loue &amp; powre, to that, that good is, &amp; therfore vſe you the means a foreſayd accordingly. Thynke that by this ſprite, you are tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe fayth coupled to Chriſt, as a lyuely member, and ſo to god, and as it were made one with him, and bi loue which ſpringeth
<pb facs="tcp:10176:14"/>
oute of this fayth, you are made one alſo with all that be of god, &amp; ſo you haue felowſhip with god and all good men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer were or ſhalbe in al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good, that god &amp; al his ſainctes, haue, or ſhall haue. Thynke as by faythe and loue through the ſpirite you are now entred into this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munyon (the bleſſednes wherof no tonge can expreſſe) ſo after thys lyfe, you ſhal firſt in ſoule, &amp; in the laſt day in bodi alſo, enioy foreuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſocietie moſte perfectly whiche now is but begon in you. Thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke then of your neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that doth ſo lytle care for this your happy eſtate, thinke vpon your ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to god for makynge you, redemyng you, calling you, and ſo louenglye adoptynge you.</p>
               <p>Thynke vpon your folyſhnes in fantaſyeng ſo muche earthelye
<pb facs="tcp:10176:15"/>
and bodely pleaſures. Thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your deafnes &amp; blindenes, which hereth not god, nor ſeeth him, he calling you ſo diligently, by his workes, woordes and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes. Thinke vpon your frowardnes whiche wyll not be led of god and his ſpirit. Thinke vpon your forgetfulnes and in conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your high eſtate, how your body is the temple of the holy ghoſte, your members, are the members of Chriſte the whole world and all thinges are youre owne. 1. Cor. 6. Therfore ſay vnto your ſoule, O ſoule A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe folowe god, contempne this worlde purpoſe wel and purſue it, longe for thy Lordes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge, be readye and watche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he com not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee vnwares. And for ſoo muche as you muſte liue to gods pleaſure ſe the voca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:10176:15"/>
&amp; ſtate of your lyfe wherto god hath called you &amp; pray god for grace, knoledg, &amp; habylitie to take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt profitable thinges in hand, wel to begyn, better to go on, &amp; beſt of al to end the ſame, to gods glory &amp; profit of your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne, and thynk that time loſt, wherin you, ſpeake or do not, or (at the leaſt) think not ſum thing to gods glorye, and your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therns commodytye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> When you goe foorth of the doers praye.</head>
               <p>NOwe muſt I walke among the ſnares of deathe, ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out of Sathan and of hys myſcheuous mynyſters, in the worlde, carryenge wyth me a frende to them bothe, and a foe to my ſelfe, euen thys bodye of ſyn and ſynfull fleſhe. O grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de Capytayne Chryſte, leade mee
<pb facs="tcp:10176:16"/>
and guyde me I beſech thee, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me from the plagues, and ſubtilties, wherof I am endaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gered. Graunt that I may take al thinges that hap as I ſhoulde doe, onely vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſet thou mine eyes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I mai ſo go on forwards in thy wai as by no thinges I be hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred, but rather forthered and may refer all thnigs to the accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinglye, ſhowe me thy ways (O Lord) and teach me thy pathes. Conſider how vainli y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part of men be occupied, how thei do troble and comber the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſly, how thei meddle w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many thinges therby much alienating thir mindes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the knoledg and cogytacyon of that whyche they ſhoulde moſt eſteme, &amp; ſo becum a let and an offence to others.</p>
               <p>As in goynge abrode, you wyll ſe that your Apparel be ſemelye
<pb facs="tcp:10176:16"/>
in the ſyght of menne, ſo ſee how ſemelye you Appere in the ſygt of god.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>☞ When you are goynge any Iorney Pray.</head>
               <p>THy soure lyfe ys a pylgry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lord we came, and to the lorde we make oure iorney, howe be yt through the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe placys and paynefull, yea perrilous waies whiche our cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell enemyes, haue and doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for vs, nowe more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtark blinde by reaſon of ſinne. O Chriſt, whiche art a moſte true lodes man and guide, and therto moſt experte, faithful and fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly do thou put out thine hande o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen mine eyes make thy hyghe wais knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me, which wai thou diddeſt firſt e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter into, out of this corruptible life, &amp; haſt fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10176:17"/>
ſame for vs to immortalytye.</p>
               <p>Thou art the waye, lead vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the father by thy ſelfe, that all we mai be one with him as thou and he together be one. Showe me the way that I ſhould walke in for I lyfte vp my ſoule vnto thee. Pſal. 144.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Or Pray thus.</head>
               <p>MErcyfull father y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art wont to ſend to thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſimple hartes, thyn angells to be their kepers, &amp; as it were gui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des as elder bretherne to watch vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thi weake childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo diddeſt thou to you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Tobias, to Iacob, to Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to Ioſua. &amp;c. O good god thogh we be much vnlike vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſo many ar our ſins) yet for thyn owne goodnes ſake ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thin holi angels, to pitch thir tentes about vs, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10176:17"/>
his ſlaues to hyde and deffende to carry vs in there handes that we come not into furder dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou through out wilt deliuer vs, for theyn owne ſake. His An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles or miniſters for them that be heirs of ſaluation, ſathan ſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not, but ſeekethe alwayes to deſtroy vs. Hebr. i. Thynke ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing how we ar ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers from our contrey from our home, from our original, I meane from god. Agayne thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your madnes that doe lyngar &amp; loyter ſo glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this our Iorneye, and pilgri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>madge. Alſo how foliſhe we ar to fantazye things whiche we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not carry with vs, and to contempe conſcience which will always be acompanyon to vs, to our ioye yf it be good, but to our ſhame, and ſorrowe yf it be euyl and corrupt, finally howe vnnaturall we ar y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10176:18"/>
ſo lytle deſyer to be at our home, to be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our onely father, maſter, fellowes and frendes. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ar aboute to receaue your meat praye.</head>
               <p>THis is a wonderful miſtery of thy worke, O maker and gouernor of the world, that thou doeſt ſuſteyne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyues of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; beaſtes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this meates, ſuerlye this power is neither in the bread nor foode, but in thy wil &amp; worde, by whiche worde all thinges doe lyeue and haue their beinges. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, how great a thing is it, that thou art able yearly to geue ſuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to ſo many creatures, this is ſpoken of by thy prophet in thy prayſes. All things loke vp to the &amp; thou geueſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meat in due cea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, thou openeſt thyen ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt with thy bleſſing euery liuing thing, thes dowtles are wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful
<pb facs="tcp:10176:18"/>
workes of thyne almightines, I therfore hertely pray the (O moſt liberal lord &amp; faithful father) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as thou by meate through thy word doeſt miniſter life to thes our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame worde with thy grace doe thou quicken our ſoules that bothe in ſoule &amp; body we may pleas the til this our mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall carcas ſhall put on immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie &amp; we ſhall nede no more anye other foode, but the onely whiche the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wilt be al in all, taſte &amp; ſe how good the lord is, bleſſe the lord (O my ſoul) which tedeth and filleth thy mouthe with good thinges. Thinke a litle howe greate gods power is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> made vs. Alſo thinke how great his wiſdome is to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vs. But moſte of all thinke how many things ar geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to our vſe, how wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful it is to geue vs lyfe, but moſte of al to propagate
<pb facs="tcp:10176:19"/>
to immortalytye the lyfe of the ſoule by his onely becke. Laſte of all thinke that god by his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for thy body wold haue the to confirme thy fayth of gods pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uidence for thy ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ In the meale time pray.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſte liberall dyſtributor of thy gyftes, which geueſt vs all kinde of good thinges to vſe, thou beynge pure geueſt pure thinges, graunt to me thy grace, that I myſe vſe not thes thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious giftes, geuen to our vſe and profites. Let vs not loue them be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe thou doeſte geue vs theſe things, but rather let vs loue the, bycauſe thou geueſt them, and for that they be neceſſary for vs, for a ceaſon tyll we come vnto thee. Graunt vs to be conuerſaunte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt thy giftes ſoberly, purely, temperatlye, holely, becauſe thou
<pb facs="tcp:10176:19"/>
arte ſuche a one, ſo ſhall not we, turne that, to the poyſon of oure ſouls, which thou haſte geuen for the medicine of our bodies, but v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thy benefites thankfully, we ſhall finde them profitable, bothe to ſoule and body, thinke that the meates &amp; drinkes ſet before you, ar geuen to you to vſe and not to abuſe, thinke they ar geuen to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fit and not to hurte you. Thinke that they are not geuen to you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but vnto others alſo by you in eatinge, and drinkinge, thinke that you, do but fede the wormes, remember the poore pryſoners, ſicke. &amp;c. as though you were in their caſe thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foode of your ſoule Chriſt body broken &amp; his bloud ſhed. Deſyer the meate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> laſteth for euer. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vi. work for it, Chriſt meate was to do his fathers will. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fowrthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10176:20"/>
               <head>¶After your meate pray thus.</head>
               <p>BY corporal meates thou doeſt ſuſteyne our corporal daylye life (redy otherwiſe to periſh) the which ſurely is a great worke but yet this is much greater more profitable, &amp; more holy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce (O Ieſu Chriſt) doeth kepe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, for this life we ought much to tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke the, &amp; becauſe thou doeſt prolong it with thy good giftes, we moſte hartely prayſe the, howe be it this life is but the way to eternal life, which we beſech y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for thy deaths ſake y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou wilt geue vs, &amp; ſo ſhal we not onely geue the (as we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes in time for te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral things but alſo eternal thankes, for eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal thinges. O graunt to vs thes our deſyers for thy mercies ſake. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thinke now that god hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the this his bleſſing of meat
<pb facs="tcp:10176:20"/>
&amp;c. and therto tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, as repent, ſo ſeke his glory, &amp; the commodytie of thy brotherne, therfore go ther aboutes but firſt pray for grace well to begyn, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider how thou haſt byn partaker of other mens labors, as of the huſband mans, the mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, the bakars, the browers, the butchers, the cookes. &amp;c. Se ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore that thou be not adroen bee, but rather ſuch a one, as may help y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyeue, yf god haue thus fed thy body, which he leueth not but for thy ſoules ſake, how can it be the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but that he wilbe much more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fede thy ſoul. Therfore take a courrage to the, and go to hym for grace accordinglye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Cogytations for about the midday tyme.</head>
               <p>AS y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body is now enuiro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on al ſides w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> light, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:10176:21"/>
See that thy mynde maye be. As god geuethe the, thus plentifully this corporall light, ſo praye him that he wyl geue the, the ſpiritual light, thinke that as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon is now moſt cleere ſo ſhall our bodies be in the day of iudgement. As now the ſon is cum to the higheſt, and therfore wilbe gyn to draw down<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde ſo is there nothinge in the worlde ſo parfect and glorious, which (when it is at the full) wyll not decreaſe &amp; ſo wear awaye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ When you cum home agayne. Praye.</head>
               <p>THer is nothing (O Lord) more lyke to thy holy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a quyet minde, thou haſt called vs oute of the troubleſome diſquietnes of the world into that thy quiet reſte &amp; peace, whiche the world cannot, geue, being ſuche a peace as paſſeth all mens vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding.
<pb facs="tcp:10176:21"/>
Howſes ar ordeyned for vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we mighte get vs in to them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the iniury of wether, from the crewelty of beaſtes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of people, &amp; from the toyls of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, O gratious father grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that through thy great mercy my body maye enter into this howſe, from outward actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but ſo that it may become buxom &amp; obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the ſoule, &amp; make no reſiſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce there agaynſt. That in ſoule and body, I may haue a godly quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; peace to prayſe the. Amen. Peace be to this howſe and to all that dwell in the ſame. Thinke what a returne &amp; how merry a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne it wilbe to come to our eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal moſte quiet and moſte happy home, then wilbe all grefe gon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, what ſo euer heare is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; ioyful, the ſame is nothing but a very ſhadow in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10176:22"/>
               <head>¶ At the ſon goyng downe pray.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Howe vnhappye ar they O Lorde on whome thy ſonne goeth downe &amp; geueth no light, I mean thy grace which is always cleer as the midday, darke night vnto them is the midday, whiche departe from the, in the is neuer night but always day light moſt cleer. This corporal ſon hath his courſes, now vp now downe, but thou (deere lord) if we doe loue the art alwais one, O that this block and vaile of ſyn were take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thear might be always cleere day in my mind. Thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as we ar not ſory whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon goeth down, by cauſe we knowe it wyll riſe agayn, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo let vs not ſorow for death, wher through the ſoule &amp; body doe pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e a ſonder for they ſhall eftſones return &amp; cum toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther agayne. So long as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon is
<pb facs="tcp:10176:22"/>
vp, wild beaſtes kepe their de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, Foxes their borows, Owls their hoals &amp;c. but when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon is down then cum they abroade. So wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and hypocrites kepe their denns in the goſpel but it beynge taken awaye then ſwarme they oute of their hoals lyke bees as this day doeth teach.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶When y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> candles be light pray.</head>
               <p>MOſte thycke &amp; darke cloudes doe Couer our myndes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thy lyght (O Lord) do dyſpell them. Thy ſon (O moſt wiſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker) is as it were a fyer brande to the worlde, thy wyſdome, wherby light commeth bothe to ſoule and bodye is a fyer brand, to the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall world. After daye when the night commeth, thou haſte geuen for the remedy of darknes a ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle After ſyn for the remedy of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance thou haſt geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy doctrine
<pb facs="tcp:10176:23"/>
which thy dere ſon hathe brought vnto vs, O thou whiche art the Author and maſter of all truethe make vs to ſe, by both the lightes ſo that the dymnes of our mindes be dryiuen cleane awaye, lyft vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs thy myrthe in our hartes Thy worde is a lanterne to my feete &amp; a lyght vnto my pathes. Thinke that the knowledge and wiſdom, that god hathe geuen vnto vs by the ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dles of this night, wherby we ſe thoſe thinges in this night, of our bodies whiche are expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for vs, maketh vs to wiſhe muche more for this doctrine of God, and when we gette yt, the more to eſteme and dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as al would be horror without candeles, ſo is thear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge but mere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fucion whear gods worde taketh not place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ When you make your ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:10176:23"/>
vnredy Praye.</head>
               <p>THis our lyfe and weake knit body by reaſon of ſynne, by a lytle and litle, wil by dyſſolued, and ſo ſhalbe reſtored to the earth whence it was taken, then wilbe an ende of this vanyty, which by our foliſhnes we haue wroughte to our ſelues, O moſte meke fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo do thou vnty vnloſe, and loſe me for thou haſte knyt me to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether that I maye perceaue my ſelffe to be made vnredy and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued and ſo maye reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber both of whome I was made and alſo whyether I go leaſt I be had vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prepared vnto thy trybunall and Iudgement ſeate, Put of tholde man with his luſtes, &amp; concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens Be content with Ioſephe to put of thy pryſon Apparel, that thou mayſt put on newe. Thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we doe willingly put of our
<pb facs="tcp:10176:24"/>
garmentes, which in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morninge we ſhall put on agayne, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the, after the night of the worlde, we ſhall receaue on out bodies agayne let vs not vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly put them of, when god by deathe ſhall call.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you enter in to your bed Praye.</head>
               <p>THe daye nowe endyd men geue them ſelues to reſt in the night and ſo this life fyneſhed we ſhal reſt in death. Nothinge is more lyke this lyfe, then euery daye, nothing more lyke deathe then ſleape, nothing more lyke to our graeue then our bed, O lord our keper &amp; defendor graunt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I nowe layeng me downe to reſte, beinge vnable to kepe my ſelfe, may be preſerued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> craftes &amp; Aſſaultes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked enemy, &amp; &amp; graunt father, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue
<pb facs="tcp:10176:24"/>
run y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> race of this liffe thowe wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of thy mercy call me vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> that I may alwais liue &amp; watch with the, now good god giue me to take my reſt in the &amp; bring to paſſe that thy gracious goodnes may be (euen in ſleape) before mine eys, that ſleaping I be not abſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the, but may haue my dreams to drawe me vnto the &amp; ſo bothe ſoule &amp; bodye, maye bee kept pure and holye for euer. I wil lay me downe in peace &amp; take my reſt. Thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as this troble<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſum daye is now paſt &amp; night cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſo reſt, bed, and pleſaunt ſleape which maketh moſt exelent prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, &amp; moſt poore peſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes a like, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tumultes, troubles te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptationes &amp; tempeſtes of this life they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleue in Chriſte haue prepared for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an heauen and reſt moſt pleaſaunte and ioyfull.
<pb facs="tcp:10176:25"/>
As you ar not a fraied to enter in to your bed, and to diſpoſe your ſelfe to ſlepe, ſo be not a fraide to dye but rather prepare your ſelfe to yt, thinke that nowe you are nerer your ende by one days ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, then you wer in the morning</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶When you feele ſlepe to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge praye.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lorde Ieſus Chriſte my watchman and keper take me to thy care graunte that my body ſlepynge, my mynde maye watche in the, and be made mery by ſum ſight of that celeſtiall &amp; heauenlye life whearin thou arte the kyng &amp; prynce together with the father &amp; the holy ghoſte. Thy Angelles &amp; holye ſoules, be moſte hapie citeſens. O purify my ſoul kepe cleane my body, that in both I may pleaſe the, ſlepinge and wakinge for euer Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10176:25"/>
               <head>¶ A mooſte frutfull Prayer for the diſperſed Church of Chriſt very neceſſary to be vſed of the godly in theſe dayes of affliction compiled by. R. P.</head>
               <p>O Moſte omnipotent magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and glorious god and father of al conſolation, we here aſſembled do not preſume to preſent and proſtrate our ſelfes be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore thy mercy ſeate in the reſpect of our owne worthines and right<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſnes, whych is all together po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted and defyled: but in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, rightouſnes and worthines of thy onlye ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, whome thou haſt gyuen vnto vs as a moſte pure and precious gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment to couer oure polution and fylthynes wyth all, to thend we myghte appere holye and Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in thy ſighte throughe hym. Wherefore in the obedience of thy
<pb facs="tcp:10176:26"/>
commandementes and in the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fidence of thy promyſes contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in thy holy worde that thow ſhalte accepte, and graunte oure prayers preſented vnto the in the fauoure of thy only ſonne our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſu Chriſte. Eyther for oure ſelfes, or for the neceſſitie of thy ſaynctes and congregation. We here congregated together do wyth one mouth and mynde moſt humblye beſeche the not onlye to pardon and forgyue vs all oure ſynnes necligences, Ignorances and iniquites, whych we fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time inceſſantlye do commytte agaynſte thy diuine maieſtye in worde, dede, and thought, ſuch is the infirmitie of oure corrupted nature: But alſo that it wolde pleaſe thee (O benyng father) to be fauorable and mercyfull vnto thy poore afflicted churche, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation
<pb facs="tcp:10176:26"/>
diſperſed throughe out the whole worlde, whiche in theſe dayes of iniquitie are oppreſſed in iuried, diſpiced, perſecuted &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted for the teſtimonye of thy worde and for the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thy lawes.</p>
               <p>And namely O Lorde and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we humbly beſeche the to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende thy mercye and fauourable countynance vpon all thoſe that are impriſoned or condemned for the cauſe of thy Goſpell: whome thou haſt choſen forthe and made worthi to glorify thy name. That eyther it maye pleaſe the to gyue them ſuche conſtancye as thou haſt gyuen to thy ſainctes &amp; mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in tyme paſte, willinglye to ſhede theyr bloud for the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of thy worde: Or els mightlye deliuer them from the tyranny of theyr enimies as thou delyuereſt
<pb facs="tcp:10176:27"/>
the condemned Daniell from the Lions, and the perſecuted Peter oute priſon, to thexeaultation of thy glory and the reioyſing of thy churche.</p>
               <p>Further more moſte benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all father we humbly beſeche the to ſtretch forthe the myghty arme into the protection and defence of all thoſe that are exiled for the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonye of thy veryte: &amp; that by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they wolde not bende theyr backes and incline theyre neckes vnder the youcke of Anthechriſt, and be poluted wyth the execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Idolatries, and blaſphemus ſuperſtitions of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly. That it would pleaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> not onlye to fede them in ſtrange co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treys, but alſo to prepare a reſting place for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as thou haſte done from tyme to tyme for thyne electe in all age is whereas they maye vnyte them
<pb facs="tcp:10176:27"/>
ſelfes together in the ſyncere my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of thy holye worde and Sacramentes to theyr ſynguler edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And in deu time reſtore them home agayne into their la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to celebrate thy prayſes, promote thy goſpell, &amp; edefye thy deſolate congregation.</p>
               <p>Conſequently O lord thou that haſt ſayd that thou wilt not breke the bruſed reide, nor quenche the ſmokynge flaxe: Be mercyfull we beſeche thee vnto all thoſe that through feare and wecknes haue denied the by diſſimulation and ypocreſie. That it may pleaſe the to ſtrenghten theyr wecke knees (thou that art the ſtrenght of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſtandethe) and lyfte vp theyr feible handes, that theire lytell ſmoke maye increaſe into a great flame and their bruſed reid into a myghtye oke, able to abyde al the
<pb facs="tcp:10176:28"/>
bolſtringe blaſtes &amp; ſtormye tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtes of aduerſyte, to thend that the vngodly do no longer triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phe ouer theyre faight, which (as they thincke) they haue vtterly quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched &amp; ſubdewed. Stirre vp thy ſtrenght in them O lorde and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them with that merciful eye, where with thou beheldes Peter, that they riſynge by repentaunce, maye become the conſtant confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of thy worde, and the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied members of thy churche. To the end that when as by thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence thou purpoſeſte to lay thy croſſe vpon them, they do no more ſeke vnlawful meanes to auoyde the ſame, but moſt willingly to be contented with patience to take it vp &amp; follow the, in what ſort ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it ſhall pleaſe the to laye the ſame vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſhoulders. Eyther by death, impriſonment or exile.
<pb facs="tcp:10176:28"/>
And that it wil pleaſe thee, not to tempte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboute their powers, but gyue them grace vtterlye to diſpayer of theyr owne ſtrenght, and wholye to depende vpon thy mercye.</p>
               <p>On the other ſyde O lord god, thou ryghtouſe Iudge, Lette not the vngodlye the enimies of thy truth continually triumphe ouer vs, as they do at this daye. Let not thyne heritage become a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche &amp; comon lawghing ſtocke vnto the impudente and wycked Papiſtes, who by all poſſyble meanes ſeke the vtter diſtruction of thy lytell ſtocke in ſhedynge, the bloude of thy ſaynctes for the teſtimonye of thy worde, ſekynge by moſte deuelyſh and damnable practices to ſubuert thy truth. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>found them O God and all theyr wicked counſelles: &amp; in the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:10176:29"/>
pyt they haue digged for other, let them be taken, that it maye be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſally knowen, that there is no counſel nor force that can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle agaynſt the lorde our god. Breke O lord the hornes of thoſe blouddy bulles of baſan. Pull down thoſe high mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taynes that eleuate them ſelfes agaynſt thee. And rote vp the rotten race of the vngodly, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that they being conſumed in the fyre of thyne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, thyne exyled Churche may in there own land find place of habitation.</p>
               <p>O Lorde delyuer oure lande whiche thou haſte geuen vs for a porcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to poſceſſe in this lyfe from the inuaſion and ſubdewynge of ſtrangers. Truthe it is we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not denye but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſynnes hathe iuſtlye deſerued this greate plage now emynent and approchynge,
<pb facs="tcp:10176:29"/>
eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands and ſubiection of that proud and beaſtly nation, that neither know the, nor fere the: and to ſerue them in a bodyly captyuyte, that haue refuſed to ſerue the in a ſpirituall libertye. Yet lorde for as much as we are aſſuredlye perſwaded by thy holye worde that thyne anger dothe not laſte for euer towardes thoſe that erneſtly repente, but in the ſtede of vengance doeſt ſhowe mercye. We mooſte penitently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche the to remoue this thy great indignation bente towardes vs, and gyue not ouer our lande, our Cytyes, Townes, and Caſtels our goodes, poceſſions &amp; ryches, our wyfes, chyldren and our own lywes into the ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. But rather O Lorde expell them our land ſubuerte there cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelles, diſſipate their deuyces and
<pb facs="tcp:10176:30"/>
delyuere vs from theire tyranny, as thou delyuereſt. Samaria fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that cruell Benadab, Ieruſalem from that blaſphemus Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib, and Betulia from that proude Holifernus.</p>
               <p>Gyue vs O Lord ſuch princes &amp; rulers, ſuche maieſtrates &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours as wil auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, erecte vp thy goſpell, ſuppreſe Idolatrye, baniſh all papiſtrye, &amp; execute iuſtice &amp; equite. Water a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn O lord thy vyne of england w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moyſture of thi holy-word, leſte it vtterly peryſhe &amp; wither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Byld vp agayn the decayed walles of thy rewyned Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy congregation in this land, leſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly do attribute oure confuſion not vnto our ſinnes (as the truthe is) but vnto our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion in religion.</p>
               <p>Remember (O Lord) that we ar
<pb facs="tcp:10176:30"/>
a perſell of thy portion, thy flocke, the inheritors of thy kingdom, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepe of thy paſture, and the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of thy ſon our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt: deale with vs therfore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cies, that al nations, kindredes, &amp; tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, may ſelebrate thy prayſes in the reſtoringe of thy rewyned church to perfection agayn, for it is thy worke (O lord) &amp; not ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; from the do we with pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende the ſame, &amp; not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fleſhly arme of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; therfore to the only is don all dominion, power and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes geuing now in our dayes and euermore. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>i. Timoth. ii. Praye in euery place lyfting vp pure ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des.</head>
               <p>OH mighty kinge, and moſte high almighty god, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father of our lorde Ieſus chriſte, whiche mercifully doeſt gouerne
<pb facs="tcp:10176:31"/>
al thinges, which thou haſt made loke downe vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful ſeade of Abraham, the children of thy choſen Iacob, Thy choſen people I doe meane, conſecrate vnto the by the anoyncting of thi holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, And apointed to thi kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e by the eternal porpoſe, free merci, and greace, but yet as ſtraungers wandring in this vile vale of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, brought forth daily, by the worldly tyrantes, like ſheape to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlaughter. O father of al fleaſhe who by thi diuine prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geſt times and ceaſons, and moſt wonderfully diſpoſeſt kingdoms, thou haſt deſtroyed Pharo, with all his horſe, and Chariottes, puf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fid vp with pride, agayenſt thy people, leadinge forth ſaffelye by the handes of thy mercie, thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louede Iſraell, thorow the highe waues of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raging waters Thou
<pb facs="tcp:10176:31"/>
oh god the lord of all hoſtes, and armis, dideſt firſt dryue awaye from the gates of thy people the blaſphemous Senacherib, ſlaing of his armye, foure ſcore and fiue thouſand by thy angil, in one night: And after bi his owne ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes befor his own Idoles, dideſt kil the ſame blaſphemous Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later, ſhowyng openly to all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pwre, towardes thi diſpiſed letel ones. Thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt trau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce forme and chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g proud Nabuchodonoſar, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enimy of thi people, into A brute beaſt, to eate graſſe, and hay, to the horable ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of all worldly tirantes, And as thou arte the father of mercies and god of all conſolacion, ſo of thy wonderful mercie dideſt thou preſerue thos thi thre ſeruauntes in Babilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bolde corage gaue theyr bodies to the fire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:10176:32"/>
thei wolde not worſhip any deade Idole, and when they were caſt into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> burning fornace, thou dideſt geue them chearful hartes, to reioyſe, and ſinge pſalmes, and ſauedeſt vnhurt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very heares of their heades, turning the flame fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to deuoure their enemies Thou oh lorde god, by the might of thy right arme (which gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all) broughteſt Daniell thi prophet ſaue into light and life, forthe of the darcke denne of the deuouring lions where by falſe accuſations he was ſhout vnder the erth, of thoſe raging beaſtes to be deuoured, but thou turnedſt ther cruelty vpon his accuſares, repainge the wickede, vpon their own pates. Yea lord which paſſeth al wonders, &amp; is far aboue mans powre to perceiue therin thy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge, thou dideſt cauſe the huge,
<pb facs="tcp:10176:32"/>
and greate dragon of the ſeas, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horrible Leuiathan, and Behe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth, the main whalefiſh, to ſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low vp and deuoure, thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Ionas, to kepe him iii. dayes and iii. nightes in the dongeon of his bealy the darke hellicke graue to a liuinge man, Thou dideſt cauſe that grete monſter, to carie him to the place, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haddeſt apoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, and ther to caſt him vp ſaue, and able to do thy maſſage. Now alſo O heauenly father, beholdor of all thinges, to whome only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth vengeaunce, thou ſeeſt &amp; conſidreſt how thy holy name by the wicked wordlinges, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Idoloters is diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid, thy ſacrate woorde, refuſed, forſaken and diſpiſed, thy holye ſprite prouokede, and offended, thy choſene temple polluted, and deffilede, Tarie not tooe longe
<pb facs="tcp:10176:33"/>
therfore, but ſhow thy powre ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delye vpon thy choſen houſehold, which is ſo greuouſly vexed, &amp; ſo cruelly handled by thy open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, Auenge thy owne glorye, and ſhorten theſe euell dayes, for thy electes ſake. Let thy kingdom come of all thy deſyred, &amp; though oure liuinges, hath offended thy maieſty, as we doe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly (O Lorde) that we haue all ſinned, our kings, princes, preſtes prophetes, and people, All we to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, wyth our pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes fathers &amp; mothers, haue moſt greuouſly, infinitely, paſſing all meſure, and number with our harde flintiſhe hartes, our diſſolute, and careles lyfe, withoute all ſhame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce for ſyn, offendid, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſid, treſpaſſid, ſynned, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted moſt horrible wickednes, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue worthely deſerued,
<pb facs="tcp:10176:33"/>
the vttermoſte of thy plages and terrible vengeaunce. Yet for thy owne glorye (O mercifull Lord) ſuffer not the enemye of thy ſonne Chryſte, the romyſhe Antichriſt, thus wretchedlye to delude, and draw fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the our poore brethern, for whome thy ſonne once died, that by his crueltie, after ſo cleare light, thei ſhold be made captiues to domme Idoles, and deuelyſh Inuentions, of popyſhe ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, therunto pertayning. Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer hym not to ſeduce the ſymple ſort with his fonde opinion, that his falſe gods, blind mumbling, fayned religion or his foliſhe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticion, doth geue hym ſuche conqueſtes, ſuche victories, ſuche triumphe, and ſo high hand ouer vs. We knowe moſte certaynely (O Lord) that it is not ther arme and powre, but our ſynnes, and
<pb facs="tcp:10176:34"/>
offences, that hath deliuered vs to their fury, And hath cauſed the to turne away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. But turne agayne, O Lorde let vs fall into thy handes otherways (ſeing thy iuſtice muſt poniſh vs) let vs fall into thy handes (as Dauid dyd chewſe) by darth, famin, or peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or what waye thou likeſt, leaſt theſe vayne Idolaters doe reioyſe, at the miſerable deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of thoſe men, whome they make proſelites, and frome thy doctrine Apoſtates, But oh lorde thy holye will be fulfilled, this is thy righteous Iudgment, to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vs wyth the tyrannical yoke of blindnes, becauſe we haue caſt away from vs, the ſweate yoke of the holeſom worde of thy ſon our ſauiour. Yet conſider the horrible blaſphemies of thyne and our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. They name a cake, ther
<pb facs="tcp:10176:34"/>
god, there Chriſt and altogether they know nothing of thy powre, they ſay in ther hartes, ther is no god, whych eyther can, or wyl de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs: wherfore O heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, the gouerner of all thinges, the Auenger of the cauſes of the poore, the fatherles, the widow &amp; of the oppreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, loke downe from heauen, with the face of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly mercies and forgeue vs al former offences, and for thy ſonne Chriſtes ſake haue mercye vpon vs, whych by the force, and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, of wicked, and blaſphemous Idolaters without cauſes apro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, are haled &amp; pulled from our owne houſes, are ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dered ſlaine and murthered, as rebelles, and traytours, like perſons pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, peſtiferous, ſedicious, peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and full of mortall poyſon, to al men contagious where we
<pb facs="tcp:10176:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
do medell no farther, but againſt the helly powres of darkenes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpirituall craftines, in heauenlye thinges, whyche wold deny the will of our god, and the powre of oure Chriſt vnto vs, we doe contend no farther, but onely for our Chriſte crucified, and the only ſaluation by his bleſſed paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, knowledging none other god none other Chriſt, or ſauiour, but onely the, the euerliuing lord and our moſt merciful father, and thy deare ſonne our ſauiour, who is in the ſame glory with the in the high heauens, Therfore O Lord for thy glorious name ſake, for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, by whome thou haſte promyſed to graunt al righteous requeſtes, make the wicked Idolaters to wonder and ſtand amaſed, at thy almightye powre, vſe thy wonted ſtrength,
<pb facs="tcp:10176:35"/>
to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion of thyne enemies, and to the healpe &amp; deliueraunce of thy perſecuted people all thy ſaintes doe beſech the therfore, the yonge infantes (which haue ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deale taſted of thy ſweete worde) by whoſe mouthes thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſed to make perfect thy praiſes whoſe Aungels doth alwaye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy face, who beſide the loſſe of vs ther parentes, Are in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to be compellid, and dryuen (wythout thy greate mercies to ſerue domme, &amp; inſenſible Idols) doe cry and call to thee: ther pite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mothers, with lamentable teares, lye proſtrate before the throne of thy grace. Thou father of the fatherles Iudge of the wid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dowes, and auenger of all the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſid, let it apere (O Lord omni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>potent) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou doeſt heare, iudge, aueng, &amp; poniſh all wronges offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:10176:36"/>
to all thy little ones that doe beleue in the, Doe this O Lorde for thy names ſake, Ariſe vp O Lord and thy enemies ſhalbe ſcatered &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, So be yt O Lord moſt mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full at thy tyme apointed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10176:36"/>
               <head>¶An other godly prayer to be ſayde at al tymes.</head>
               <p>HOnor and prayſe be geuen to the o Lorde god almighty moſt dere father of heauen, for all thy marſys and louinge kindneſſe ſhowyd vnto vs, in that it hath pleyſyd thy gracius good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes frely and of thine own accord to electe and choſe vs to ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before the beginning of the world, and euen lyke contenewall than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the for creatynge of vs after thyne owne ymage, for redeminge, vs with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precius bludde of thy derſonne when we ware vtterly loſt, for ſanctefieng vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy holy ſprit in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reuelacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and knowlege of thy holy worde, for helping and Suckering vs in all our needes and neſceſites, for ſauinge vs frome all daungers
<pb facs="tcp:10176:37"/>
of bodie and ſowle, for conforting vs ſo fatherly in al our tribulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and perſecucions, for ſparing vs ſo long and geuinge vs ſo large a time of repentans, thes benifites O moſt mercyfull father, lyke as we knowlege to haue receuid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy only goodnes, euen ſo we beſeche the that for thy dere ſonne Ieſus Chriſtes ſake to graunt vs alwayſe thy holy ſprit, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we maye contenewally growe in tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kefulnes towardes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, to be ledde into all truthe, and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyd in all oure aduerſetes, O lord ſtrenthen oure faithe, kindell it more in faruentnes and loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the &amp; our neyghbors for thy ſake. Suffer vs not dereſte father to receiue thy worde any more in vayne, but graunt vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayſe the aſſyſtans of thy grace and holye ſprit, that in hart word
<pb facs="tcp:10176:37"/>
and deede, we maye ſantefye and doe worſhype to thy holy name. Helpe to amplefye &amp; encreſſe thy kyngdome, and what ſoeuer thou ſendeſte we maye be hartely well content wyth thy good pleaſure and wyll, lette vs not lacke the thynge (Oh father) wyth oute the whyche we cannot ſerue the, but bleſſe thou ſo al the works of our handes that we maye haue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and not to be chargeabell but rather helpfull vnto others, be mercyfull (O Lorde) to our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and ſeyng our det yt gret whych thou haſte forgeuen vs in Ieſus chriſt, make vs to loue the and our neyghbors ſo muche the more. Be thou oure father our captayne and defender in all te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions holde thou vs by thy mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyfull hande, that we maye be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from all inconueniences,
<pb facs="tcp:10176:38"/>
&amp; end our lyues in the ſantefyeng and honor of thy holye name, thorough Ieſu Chriſt our lorde, and only ſauiour. Amen.</p>
               <p>Let thy mighty hande and out ſtrechyd arme O Lorde be ſtyll oure defence, thy mercy &amp; louinge kindnes in Ieſu Chriſt thy dere ſonne our ſaluacion, thy trew and holye worde our inſtruction, thy grace and holye ſprite, our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolacion, vnto the end, and in the end. Amen.</p>
               <p>¶ O Lord increſe our fayth.</p>
               <p>Bradfords beades that he prayed on being in Priſon for the teſtimoni, of Ieſus Chriſt leaui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them as neceſſary to be vſid of the faythfull.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10176:38"/>¶Bleſyd ar the dead that dye in the lord, euen ſo ſaith the Spiret, that they reſt from theyr labores, but theyre workes folow them. <bibl>Apo. xiiii.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London in Saint Martins pariſhe in the vinetre, vpon the three Crane warfe, by wyllyam Coplande.</p>
            <p>Anno. Do. M.D.LIX. the xv. daye of Marche.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
